all right
[Music]
what is the optimal exercise timing for
weight loss is it better to exercise in
the morning or the evening before
breakfast or after breakfast there was a
Nobel prize-winning exercise
physiologist who said he always ran a
mile every morning before breakfast was
he right let's find out more than a
dozen experiments have been published
compared to the amount of fat burned in
a fasted versus fed State and every
single one the more fat was burned on an
empty stomach on average a single bout
of low to moderate intensity activity
before a meal burned off three grams
more fat than the same amount of
exercise after a meal that's about three
quarters of a pat of Butters worth of
fat enough to improve insulin
sensitivity same amount of exercise but
more fat loss all because of timing now
just because you burn more fat while
you're exercising doesn't necessarily
mean you end up with less fat at the end
of the day maybe your body offsets the
extra fat loss that occurs during
exercise with a little extra fat storage
when you finally do it balancing it out
researchers in Japan set out to
investigate the possibility that your
body makes up for it later by measuring
24-hour fat balance after 100 minutes of
running either before breakfast or after
lunch on the exercise after lunch day
they burned a total of 608 calories of
fat over the course of that day
in contrast the exercise before
breakfast days in the same 24-hour
period they burned through nearly 90
percent more
1142 calories of straight fat so the
next day they woke up with about a
quarter cup of fat less after the same
amount of exercise that's remarkable
what about just something like walking
60 minutes before breakfast after lunch
or after dinner over the 24 hours they
exercised in the evening 432 calories
were burned off on the afternoon
exercise day they burned out 446
calories of fat they also had a control
day with no exercise at all and on that
day they burned through 456 fat calories
that's disappointing it's like they
never walked at all but the same amount
of exercise before breakfast resulted in
717 calories of fat loss over the course
of the day timing matters so much so
that when it comes to an hour of walking
exercise increases 24-hour fat burning
only when it's performed before
breakfast here's the fat balance graph
with no exercise you can see the fat
storage bump up at breakfast lunch and
supper before slowly coming back down
overnight
exercise in the afternoon or evening and
end up with more fat than not exercising
at all but exercise in the morning and
at least your fat balance comes back to
Baseline
all such similar studies on both men and
women should we burn through more fat on
the days we exercised before rather than
after eating after reading the
chronobiology chapter though or watching
my chronobiology videos in alternative
explanation May spring to mind maybe
it's just a morning thing maybe it has
nothing to do with meals in your
circadian rhythm is just dictating the
difference no exercising in the morning
after breakfast appears no better than
exercising in the evening after dinner
and exercising before breakfast works
better than immediately after breakfast
both still in the morning it really does
seem to be a pre versus post-meal effect
but why
carbohydrate is the preferred fuel of
the body when you eat sugars or starches
they get broken down and converted into
blood sugar after a meal blood sugars
rise and your muscles are quick to
snatch it up for fuel without having to
rely much on your energy stores if you
instead take a siesta and your muscles
have no immediate need for energy the
excess blood sugar from meal can be
stored in our muscles in the form of
glycogen for later use
glycogen is just a bunch of blood sugar
molecules strung together into a massive
branches that can be broken off and used
for quick bursts of energy anytime we
need them
if you exercise after a meal your
muscles can siphon off some of the extra
blood sugar floating around for energy
before a meal your muscles have to
instead resort to dipping into your
energy stores and end up burning mostly
a combination of glycogen and fat that
explains why you burn more fat during
fasted exercise but what about all the
extra fat burned throughout the rest of
the day
glycogen
is more than a store
glycogen isn't just an energy Reserve
but acts as a sensor capable of
activating metabolic pathways exercising
before breakfast can exhaust as much as
18 percent of your glycogen stores and
that depletion can act as a powerful
rallying cry to your fatty tissues to
start pulling more of their own weight
by breaking down more fat the lower
glycogen stores fall the greater the
sustained 24-hour fat loss
how long do you have to go without food
in order to trigger this effect
six hours may be sufficient so it
doesn't have to be before breakfast if
you timed it right you could exercise
before a late lunch or if you had an
early enough lunch maybe before dinner
when you get home from work
if exercise in a faceted state isn't
possible doesn't matter what you eat
insulin release after a meal appears to
play a critical role in suppressing fat
breakdown explaining why lower glycemic
foods in this case muesli versus Corn
Flakes can have less of an effect
lentils were identified as a promising
option for maintaining athletic
endurance which can take a hit on an
empty stomach while maintaining more of
the fat dissolution
lentils are said to be unlikely to be
consumed by the general population due
to quote unquote low palatability they
obviously haven't tried my mom's lentil
soup it's worth mentioning that although
there's increased 24-hour fat burning
exercising in a fasted State the only
way to see if this facilitates weight
loss over time
is to put it to the test which we'll
explore next
please
[Music]
foreign